Guide to the Corcoran Gallery of Art and Corcoran College of Art + Design, Corcoran Gallery of Art conservation department records, circa 1882-2019 COR0005.2.RG
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Dare Myers Hartwell records, 1982-2013, 2019; Series 5
  - Conservation grants and financial records, 1984-2013; Series 5 Subseries 3
    This subseries contains grant applications, reports, and files for various grants to the Corcoran Gallery from the Getty Trust, Institute of Museum Services, and The National Endowment for the Arts for conservation and restoration of works in the collection, as well as general financial records for the Conservation department. Records date from 1984-2013.
    - Getty Trust: Conservation of Barye bronzes, 1987-1988; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Getty Trust: Condition survey of antiquities, 1987-1991; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Getty Trust: Condition survey of antiquities - Collection survey, 1988; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folders 3-7)
    - Institute of Museum Services: Conservation of Loire tapestries, 1985-1986; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Institute of Museum Services: Paper conservation project for drawings in the permanent collection, 1986-1988; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Institute of Museum Services: Clark collection carpet survey and conservation, 1990-1991; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Institute of Museum Services: Corcoran photography collection condition survey and improvements to housing and storage, 1995; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - The National Endowment for the Arts: Conservation of Albert Bierstadt's Last of the Buffalo, 1983-1985; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - The National Endowment for the Arts: Conservation equipment purchase, 1984-1985; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - The National Endowment for the Arts: Conservation equipment purchase, 1985-1986; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - The National Endowment for the Arts: Museum programs, paper condition survey, 1986-1987; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - The National Endowment for the Arts: Care of collections, conservation of American neoclassical sculpture, 1987-1988; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - The National Endowment for the Arts: Care of collections, conservation of paper, 1988-1990; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - Conservation studio planning, 1990-2002; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Long range planning, 1995-2012; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - PPDS, 2000-2002; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - Dutch paintings exam, 2008; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - Conservation fundraising, 2011; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 22)
    - UMD and the Corcoran conservation department partnership, 2013; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 7, Folder 23)
    - Architectural blueprints - treatment proposal, 1995; Series 5 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Salon Dore restoration files, 1952-2012; Series 5 Subseries 4
    This subseries contains reports, correspondence, publications, and audiovisual materials documenting the condition and restoration projects of the Salon Dore, the Corcoran's 18th-century French period room donated to the Corcoran in 1926 as part of the bequest of Montana Senator William A. Clark. Records date from 1952-2012.
    Related Materials
    Series 5 Subseries 6 of this collection has treatment reports for work done on Salone Dore and the tables in November 2019.
    - Salon Dore - Copies of Important Documents, 1952-1990; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Salon Dore Restoration, 1954; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Salon Dore Restoration - Funding, 1980-1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Salon Dore - Old Restoration Projects, 1983-1984; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Salon Dore Restoration - General Correspondence, 1988-1989; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Salon Dore - General Correspondence, 1990-1992; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Salon Dore - General Correspondence, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Salon Dore - General Correspondence, 1994-1999; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Gohard and Fancelli, 1989; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Gohard and Fancelli, 1992; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - Gohard and Fancelli, 1993-1999; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - Ateliers Gohard gold-leaf work, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Salon Dore Publicity, 1991-1999; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Reopening dinner, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Salon Dore Symposium, 1993 November 12; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - Salon Dore Symposium - 4 cassettes, 1993 November 12; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - Sotheby's Event, 1994; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - Bruno Pons, 1994-1997; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - Dare Hartwell's Salon Dore Article, 1994-1997; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - Salon Dore Publication Illustrations, 1995-1997; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - Salon Dore - Publication, 1996-1998; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - Andre Baeyens Salon Dore Article, 1996; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - Publication event, 1998-1999; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    - Lighting - George Sexton, 2000; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - Restoration Costs, 2001; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - Salon Dore Diagrams, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Salon Dore Consolidation William Lewin and Davida Rouner, 2012; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    - Salon Dore: Consolidation After Restoration, 1997-2000; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    - Salon Dore corner tables - consolidation, 2012; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    - Boiserie: Before treatment prints, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 30)
    - Negatives/Color Transparencies Boiserie Before Treatment, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 31)
    - B&W Negatives: Garlands Cleaned, 1993 March 5; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 32)
    - Boiserie During Treatment Negatives, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 33)
    - Boiserie After Treatment Negatives Color Transparencies, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 34)
    - Boiserie: During Treatment Prints, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 35)
    - Ceiling mural prints, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 36)
    - Ceiling Mural Prints, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 37)
    - Salon Dore Ceiling Before & After Treatment B/W Negs, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 8, Folder 38)
    - Ceiling Mural Color Transparencies, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Salon Dore Doors, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Doors: Before and During Treatment Prints, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Salon Dore Doors Negatives, 1989; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Ormolu Hardware Salon Dore, 1989-1992; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - French Salon Marble: Mantle and Baseboard, 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Dessus-De-Portes Condition Report, 1990; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - Boiserie-Sconces, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - Ateliers Gohard and Fancelli, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - Salon Dore Analytical Reports Ceiling/Doors, 1990; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Salon Dore Analytical Reports Boiserie, 1992; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Richard Woolbers notebooks, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folders 12-15)
    - Columbia University, 1987-1991; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 16)
    - Examination and Analysis of Decorative Interior Finishes at "the French Room", 1989 March 31; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 17)
    - Columbia Analysis of Decorative Finishes, 1988 April 20; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 18)
    - Columbia University Analysis of Decorative FInishes, 1988 March 31; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 19)
    - The Mural of the French Room: Pilot Treatments and Recommendations for Conservation, 1990 May 21; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 20)
    - The Ceiling of the French Room, 1988 May 15; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Constance Siwer Diagrams, circa 1988; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Salon Dore Ceiling treatment - disassembled binder, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folders 23-26)
    - Salon Dore Ceiling treatment photographs - disassembled binder, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folders 27-29)
    - Salon Dore Boiserie treatment - disassembled binder, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folders 30-33)
    - Salon Dore Boiserie treatment photographs - disassembled binder, circa 1993; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 9, Folders 34-36)
    - French Period Room, 1990 December 7; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 1-4)
    - French Room restoration, 1991 February 1; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 5-8)
    - Salon Dore, 1991 April 2; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 9-14)
    - Salon Dore, 1991 June 21; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 15-17)
    - Salon Dore, 1991 July 22; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 18)
    - Salon Dore, 1991 July 23; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 19)
    - Period Room #1, 1992 February 19; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 20-21)
    - Corcoran Period Room, 1993 March 10; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 22-23)
    - Corcoran, 1993 April 30; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 24)
    - Interview with Philip Equy, 1993 April 30; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 25)
    - Student Amy Farina on cornice, Gwenael Bourse, 1993 April 30; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 26)
    - Corcoran, 1993 May 21; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 27-30)
    - Corcoran, 1993 October 13; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 31)
    - Doors in lab, 1993 October 13; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 32)
    - Guilding, Arts and Sciences panel, 1993 October 13; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 33)
    - Corcoran Period Room #3, Undated; Series 5 Subseries 4 (Box 10, Betacam 34)
  - Nature Conservancy Exhibition files, 2006; Series 5 Subseries 5
    This subseries contains files from two disassembled binders and a CD pertaining to condition reports for artworks loaned to the exhibition "In Response to Place: Photographs from the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places" in 2006.
    - In Response to Place: Photographs from the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places, condition report part 1, 2006; Series 5 Subseries 5 (Box 7, Folders 24-29)
    - In Response to Place: Photographs from the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places, condition report part 2, 2006; Series 5 Subseries 5 (Box 7, Folders 30-32)
    - The Nature Conservancy In Response to Place: Photographs from the Nature Conservancy's Last Great Places (Looped), 2006; Series 5 Subseries 5 (Box 7, Cd 33)
  - Dare Myers Hartwell Conservation Consulting Services treatment reports, 2019 November; Series 5 Subseries 6; Hartwell, Dare Myers, 1944 -
    This subseries contains conditional assessment of the Salon Dore, four tables that are part of the room, and a report of conservation work done to the Cocoran lions that flank the entrace to the Corcoran building. These reports and conservation work was completed under the management of Dare Myers Hartwell. The reports are dated November 2019.
    Conservation and restoration; Salon Dore; Hartwell, Dare Myers, 1944 -
    - Corcoran lions, 2019 November; Series 5 Subseries 6 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Salon Dore, 2019 November; Series 5 Subseries 6 (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Salon Dore tables, 2019 November; Series 5 Subseries 6 (Box 12, Folder 3)
- Conservation files transferred from the National Gallery of Art, 1882-2010; Series 6
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Records in this subseries were donated to GWU by the National Gallery between 2016-2019.
  This series is arranged in three subseries: Painting conservation files for non-Corcoran works of art; Conservation files for deaccessioned works of art; and Conservation files for building objects and details.
  This subseries contains conservation files for non-Corcoran artworks owned by private individuals and organizations, conservation files for artworks deaccessioned by or loaned to the Corcoran Gallery in the course of its operation, and conservation files for objects and elements of the Corcoran Gallery building. Records date from 1882-2010.
  - Painting conservation files for non-Corcoran works of art, 1984-2003; Series 6 Subseries 1
    Files are arranged alphabetically by artist's last name.
    This subseries contains conservation treatment and condition reports for works of art not owned by the Corcoran but treated by Corcoran conservation staff. Records date from 1984-2003.
    - Bierstadt, Albert - California Scenery Sunset View, 2013; Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Birch, Thomas - Upper Ferry Bridge at Fairmont, Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Green, Jonathan - Daughters of the South, Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Hyland, B.A. - Portrait of a Dog, Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - McLeod, William - Glimpse of Washington, D.C., Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Peale, Charles Wilson - Germantown Mill Scene Meadow and Road in Germantown, Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Weir, J.F. - Niagra Falls, Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - Woodside, John - Lemon Hill, Series 6 Subseries 1 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Conservation files for deaccessioned and loaned works of art, 1983-2011; Series 6 Subseries 2
    This subseries contains conservation treatment and condition reports for works of art deaccessioned by the Corcoran Gallery or loaned to the Corcoran Gallery for exhibition. Records date from 1983-2011.
    - Albee, Percy - Mining, 1999; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Alexander, Francis - Globe Village, 1986; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 11)
    - Bierstadt, Albert - California Scenery- Sunset View, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 12)
    - Bubley, Esther - White waiting room, 2005; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 13)
    - Chagall, Marc - La Parade Flueri, 2000; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 14)
    - Copley, John Singleton - Colonel Jacob Fowle, 1983-2010; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folders 15-18)
    - Corot, Jean Baptiste Camille (attributed) - Boat in Moonlight, 1988; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Corot, Jean Baptiste Camille (attributed) - The Farmhouse in the Elder Trees, Normandy, 1988; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 21)
    - Corot, Jean Baptiste Camille (formerly attributed) - The Coliseum seen from the Farnese Gardens, 1985; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 22)
    - Cuyp, Albert (formerly attributed) - View of Wageningen, 2011; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 23)
    - Daphnis, Nassos - Epoxy on masonite, 2002; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 24)
    - Davis, Charles Harold - Summer Pastoral, 1997; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 25)
    - DeCarava, Roy - Some folks selling, 2005; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 26)
    - Dunoyer de Segonzac, Andre - Still Life (A Small Bowl of Flowers, a Cheese, Carrots, Bottle and a Pot), 1983; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 27)
    - Erwitt, Elliot - South Carolina, 2005; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 28)
    - Evans, Walker - Pressing Club, 2003; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 29)
    - Frank, Robert - London, 2004; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 30)
    - Goyen, Jan Josephsz van - A Shipping Scene, 2002; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Hals, Frans (circle of) - Woman with Flagon, 2011; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 32)
    - Heda, Willem Claesz - Still Life, 1984; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 33)
    - Hunt, William Morris - Rapids, Sister Islands, 2009; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 34)
    - Inness, George - Tenafly, Autumn, 1988; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 35)
    - Jarvis, J.F. - Cabinet card, CGA, 1999; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 36)
    - Lewis, Robert exhibition, 2004; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 37)
    - Meatyard, Ralph Eugene, 2005; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 38)
    - Middaugh, Robert - Untitled, 2000; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 39)
    - Motherwell, Robert - Roll of the Dice, 2001; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 40)
    - Neri, Manuel - Untitled, 1996; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 41)
    - Neri, Manuel - Various works, 1995; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 42)
    - Nutt, Craig - Banana Pepper, 2002; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 43)
    - Oldenburg, Claes - Pizza, 2001; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 44)
    - Rattner, Abraham - Ospedalette, Italia study the sea, 1998; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 45)
    - Rockwell, Norman - Four Freedoms tear sheet, 2004; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 46)
    - Ruley, Ellis - Accident, 1995; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 47)
    - Sawyer, Wells Moses - Winter at Snug Rock, 2010; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 48)
    - Seymour, Samuel - The City of New York, 1986; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 49)
    - Stettner, Louis - Penn Station, 2005; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 50)
    - Topkapi - Hilkey-i Saadet Calligraphic Panel, 2000; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 51)
    - Unknown - Andirons, 1993; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 52)
    - Unknown - Maiolica, 1991-2007; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folders 53-54)
    - van Dyck workshop, Style of Anthony - Portrait of Charles Lewis, Elector Palatine, Eldest Son of the King of Bohemia, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 55)
    - Vander Zee - Untitled, 2004; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 56)
    - Various artists - Biennial exhibition, 1997; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 57)
    - Various artists - Corcoran Gallery Miniatures, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 58)
    - Weber, Max - Abstract Machine Forms, 1992; Series 6 Subseries 2 (Box 11, Folder 59)
  - Conservation files for building objects and details, 1882-2010; Series 6 Subseries 3
    This subseries contains conservation treatment reports for objects and building details of the Corcoran Gallery, in particular the lion statues framing the entrance to the Corcoran building, fireplace mantel details, dedication plaque, and Parthenon frieze installed in the atrium. Records date from 1882-2010.
    - Corcoran lions bronze - copies of Canova, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 60)
    - After Canova - Corcoran lions - Conservation report, 1997 August; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 61)
    - After Canova - Corcoran lions - treatment photos, 1997; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 62)
    - After Canova - Corcoran lions - Color interior, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 63)
    - After Canova - Corcoran lions - Black and White - before, during, and after treatment, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 64)
    - After Canova - Corcoran lions - Color - before, during, and after treatment, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 65)
    - After Canova - Corcoran lions - Conservation reports and notes after 1997, 1998-2010; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 66)
    - Black and White negatives - Documentation of conservation treatment of Bronze Lions by Norton Art Conservation, Inc., 1997; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 67)
    - Color negatives - Documentation of conservation treatment of Bronze Lions by Norton Art Conservation, Inc., 1997; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 68)
    - Photo documentation: Bronze lions and marble pedestals, Flagg's design of the Corcoran, and Limestone Columns in th eGallery's North Atrium, 1997 March; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 69)
    - Color slides of the Corcoran Bronze Lions, 1997; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 70)
    - After Canova - Two Lions, 1882-2010; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 19)
    - Atrium frieze from the Parthenon, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 72)
    - Fireplace in Director's Conference Room, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 73)
    - Flagg building dedication plaque, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 74)
    - Mantel, Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 75)
    - Mantel (Unknown, French), Undated; Series 6 Subseries 3 (Box 11, Folder 76)